<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Video | anselmolsm.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://anselmolsm.org/blog/categories/video/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://anselmolsm.org/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-29T16:57:22-02:00</updated>
  <id>http://anselmolsm.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Anselmo L. S. Melo]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Qt State Machine and Animated Layouts Integration]]></title>
    <link href="http://anselmolsm.org/blog/qt-state-machine-and-animated-layouts-integration/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-03T00:00:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://anselmolsm.org/blog/qt-state-machine-and-animated-layouts-integration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hey! Another post regarding our work with <a href="" title="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qt_(toolkit)">Qt</a> <a href="http://labs.trolltech.com/page/Projects/Graphics/Kinetic">Kinetic</a> here at <a href="http://www.openbossa.org/">openbossa</a> - <a href="http://www.indt.org.br/">INdT</a>.</p>

<p>A quick introduction:  in the end of February I <a href="http://www.anselmolsm.org/blog/layout-animations-with-qt-kinetic/">posted</a> <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M3HbmrNvQl4">video</a> showing the first example of layouts animations.  At that time, the API wasn't complete and there was no integration with states and some stuff were hardcoded.</p>

<p>In March some <a href="http://www.qtsoftware.com/">Trolls</a> visited Recife to speak at <a href="http://www.bossaconference.org/">Bossa Conference 2009</a> (you can watch the presentations at <a href="http://openbossa.blip.tv">http://openbossa.blip.tv</a>. It was nice because we could talk about the work we're doing together using whiteboards, what makes a huge difference =) .</p>

<p>After Bossa, we continued the development of the Animated Layouts API, making layout proxies transparent and integrating with the <a href="http://doc.trolltech.com/solutions/4/qtstatemachine/statemachine-api.html">Qt State Machine Framework</a>. It now allows the customization of animations per widget, bringing more flexibility in the creation of rich user interfaces using Qt.</p>

<p>The following video shows the <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M3HbmrNvQl4">old example</a> with these improvements:
<iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/wZo1wskBs0A?color=white&theme=light"></iframe></p>

<p>After that, we created some examples in order to show use cases and also to test what had been developed, but it is the next post's subject! (remember what I said in the beginning? ;) )</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Canola2 menu layout with Qt Kinetic]]></title>
    <link href="http://anselmolsm.org/blog/canola2-menu-layout-with-qt-kinetic/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-03T00:00:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://anselmolsm.org/blog/canola2-menu-layout-with-qt-kinetic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back dear readers. This is my second post of the day talking about what is happening in the development of animated layouts in <a href="http://labs.trolltech.com/page/Projects/Graphics/Kinetic">Qt Kinetic</a>.</p>

<p>As I said in my <a href="http://www.anselmolsm.org/blog/qt-state-machine-and-animated-layouts-integration/">previous post</a>, we discussed about new good examples that could show use cases of this new API. In the end, only one example was created, but it's really cool =) .</p>

<p>Maybe some of you will recognize this interface, it looks like <a href="http://openbossa.indt.org.br/canola/index.html">canola2</a>'s main menu, another software developed by <a href="http://www.indt.org.br/">INdT</a> for Nokia <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Tablet">internet tablets</a> (e.g. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/N810">N810</a>) - and as you can read <a href="http://etrunko.blogspot.com/2009/03/canola-is-free.html">here</a>, an <a href="https://bugs.maemo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=3881">old bug was fixed</a> and canola2 is now a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_software">free software</a>, released under <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gplv3#Version_3">GPLv3</a>. In <a href="http://wouwlabs.com/blogs/jeez/?p=99">this post</a> you can read more about the development of that interface.</p>

<p>So, we wrote an example based on that concept. During the development we had nice discussions regarding the algorithm for the engine that controls the icons distribution on the screen.</p>

<p>Check it out:
<iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/eJcTBJaPRZg?color=white&theme=light"></iframe></p>

<p>The source code is not available yet, but it will be published soon in a git repository near you, then you will be able to check how animated layouts were used and also see that algorithm I've just mentined. So, stay tuned!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Layout Animations with Qt Kinetic]]></title>
    <link href="http://anselmolsm.org/blog/layout-animations-with-qt-kinetic/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-26T00:00:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://anselmolsm.org/blog/layout-animations-with-qt-kinetic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My first post about stuff I'm working on ;)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.openbossa.org/">We</a> are working together with <a href="http://www.qtsoftware.com/">Qt Software</a> guys in the <a href="http://labs.trolltech.com/page/Projects/Graphics/Kinetic">Qt Kinetic</a> project, specifically with animated layout transitions.</p>

<p>Last week we made our first demo of what is being developed. It uses the basics we've just finished, now we're working to define the final API.  The following video shows this demo:</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/M3HbmrNvQl4?color=white&theme=light"></iframe></p>

<p>Interested? Read this <a href="http://blog.morpheuz.cc/26/02/2009/animated-layouts-with-qt-kinetic/">overview</a> and <a href="http://blog.eduardofleury.com/archives/2009/02/51/">more details about internals</a> written by co-workers, then join us at #qt-kinetic @ Freenode =)</p>

<p>PS: <portuguese>Há também uma visão geral em português a respeito <a href="http://wouwlabs.com/blogs/jeez/?p=62">neste post</a>. </portuguese></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Opera Mini - PSP]]></title>
    <link href="http://anselmolsm.org/blog/opera-mini-psp/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-25T00:00:00-02:00</updated>
    <id>http://anselmolsm.org/blog/opera-mini-psp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Se você é mais um dos que acham que o browser que vem com o <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PlayStation_Portable">PSP</a> é triste, eis uma alternativa: Utilizar o <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opera_mini">Opera Mini</a>. Sim, aquele que também dá pra usar em celulares. Para isso é necessário instalar o <a href="http://www.pspkvm.com-a.googlepages.com/">PSPKVM</a> (uma máquina virtual <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java_Platform,_Micro_Edition">Java ME</a> para PSP) e de dentro dele instalar e executar o Opera mini. Mais detalhes (incluindo links para downloads) em <a href="http://my.opera.com/community/blog/2008/10/22/a-better-browser">http://my.opera.com/community/blog/2008/10/22/a-better-browser</a>.</p>

<p>A utilização do Opera Mini no começo é bem chata pois as posições dos comandos na tela não correspondem com os botões do PSP, mas com um pouco de treino melhora. Por exemplo, para inserir a URL na barra de endereços os comandos necessários são:</p>

<p><strong>select</strong>, para abrir o menu lateral e <strong>select</strong> novamente para selecionar a opção <em>Enter Address</em>. Com a barra de endereços selecionada, use o direcional analógico para exibir as opções <em>Search</em> e <em>Insert symbol... . </em>A segunda opção exibirá um teclado qwerty que facilitará inserção de caracteres. O direcional analógico navega entre as teclas do teclado virtual. Terminada a edição da URL, aperte <strong>start</strong> e entao selecione <em>OK</em> no menu. Na sequência, use o botão "<strong>O</strong>" para acessar o endereço inserido.</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/uUlw6xWZVkM?color=white&theme=light"></iframe></p>

<p>Enfim, tem lá suas chatices, mas também algumas vantagens.</p>

<p>Alguma outra sugestão de browser para o PSP?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Avast, salty sea-dog!]]></title>
    <link href="http://anselmolsm.org/blog/avast-salty-sea-dog/"/>
    <updated>2008-09-19T00:00:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://anselmolsm.org/blog/avast-salty-sea-dog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>19/09: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk_like_a_pirate_day">Talk like a pirate day!</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.talklikeapirate.com/">http://www.talklikeapirate.com/</a></p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="420" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/fqMu6e5Dgtg?color=white&theme=light"></iframe></p>

<p>Arroy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
